Guide to the Eugenius Aristides Nisbet Papers, 1804-1934
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Eugenius Aristides Nisbet papers, 1804-1934
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nisbet, Eugenius Aristides, 1803-1871.
Extent: 15,909 Items
Lawyer, U. S. Representative and Confederate representative, of Macon, Ga. Correspondence, legal notebooks, bankbooks, family albums, genealogical charts, memorabilia, and other items, of Nisbet and of his family. The bulk of the collection consists of largely routine legal correspondence of Nisbet, of his son, James Taylor Nisbet, lawyer and editor, and of his brother, James Alexander Nisbet. Other papers relate to social life and customs in 19th century Georgia, political events after the Civil War, soldiers' views of the Spanish-American War, the education of girls in the early 20th century, and Nisbet family genealogy. Includes personal correspondence of Junius Wingfield Nisbet and a diary (1873-1879) of John W. Nisbet. Correspondents include Charles L. Bartlett, H. B. Battle, William Horn Battle, Allen D. Candler, W. C. Dawson, Charles H. Herty, Walter B. Hill, Malcolm Johnston, Alexander R. Lawton, John M. Kell, Wilson Lumpkin, Howard E. Rondthaler, William Schley, Hoke Smith, and James M. Smith. Also includes a transcription of a land conveyance allowing the state of Georgia to purchase 1134 acres of land from Major-General Anthony Wayne.
RL.00952
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Eugenius Aristides Nisbet Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1947.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, legal notebooks, bankbooks, family albums, genealogical charts, memorabilia, and other items, of Nisbet and of his family. The bulk of the collection consists of largely routine legal correspondence of Nisbet, of his son, James Taylor Nisbet, lawyer and editor, and of his brother, James Alexander Nisbet. Other papers relate to social life and customs in 19th century Georgia, political events after the Civil War, soldiers' views of the Spanish-American War, the education of girls in the early 20th century, and Nisbet family genealogy. Includes personal correspondence of Junius Wingfield Nisbet and a diary (1873-1879) of John W. Nisbet. Correspondents include Charles L. Bartlett, H. B. Battle, William Horn Battle, Allen D. Candler, W. C. Dawson, Charles H. Herty, Walter B. Hill, Malcolm Johnston, Alexander R. Lawton, John M. Kell, Wilson Lumpkin, Howard E. Rondthaler, William Schley, Hoke Smith, and James M. Smith. Also includes a transcription of a land conveyance allowing the state of Georgia to purchase 1134 acres of land from Major-General Anthony Wayne.
Subject Headings
Nisbet, Eugenius Aristides, 1803-1871; Wayne, Anthony, 1745-1796; Nesbitt family; Lawyers -- Correspondence; Lawyers -- Georgia -- Macon; Spanish-American War, 1898 -- Personal narratives; Women -- Education -- United States; Georgia -- Genealogy; Georgia -- Social life and customs; Macon (Ga.) -- History; United States -- Politics and government -- 1865-1900
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1804-1934, (52 boxes)
  - 1799-1848, (6 folders, Also includes transcription of conveyance, Edward Telfair to Anthony Wayne, Aug. 6th, 1786) (Box 1)
  - 1849-1854, (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1855-Mar. 1856, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Apr. 1856-Mar. 1857, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Apr.-Oct. 1857, (4 folders) (Box 5)
  - Nov. 1857-Sept. 1858, (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Oct. 1858-Mar. 1859, (4 folders) (Box 7)
  - Apr.-Oct. 1859, (4 folders) (Box 8)
  - Nov. 1859-Apr. 1860, (4 folders) (Box 9)
  - May-Nov. 1860, (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - Dec. 1860-Dec. 1861, (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1862-June 1864, (5 folders) (Box 12)
  - July 1864-Fe.b 1866, (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - Mar.-Aug. 1866, (5 folders) (Box 14)
  - Sept.-Dec. 1866, (4 folders) (Box 15)
  - Jan.-Mar. 1867, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Apr.-Sept. 1867, (4 folders) (Box 17)
  - Oct.-Dec. 1867, (3 folders) (Box 18)
  - Jan.-Mar. 1868, (4 folders) (Box 19)
  - Apr.-July 1868, (4 folders) (Box 20)
  - Aug.-Dec. 1868, (4 folders) (Box 21)
  - Jan.-Mar. 1869, (3 folders) (Box 22)
  - Apr.-Aug. 1869, (4 folders) (Box 23)
  - Sept.-Dec. 15, 1869, (5 folders) (Box 24)
  - Dec. 16, 1869-Apr. 1870, (4 folders) (Box 25)
  - May-Sept. 1870, (3 folders) (Box 26)
  - Oct. 1870-Feb. 1871, (4 folders) (Box 27)
  - Mar.-June 1871, (4 folders) (Box 28)
  - July-Oct. 1871, (4 folders) (Box 29)
  - Nov. 1871-Feb. 1872, (4 folders) (Box 30)
  - Mar.-June 1872, (3 folders) (Box 31)
  - July-Nov. 1872, (3 folders) (Box 32)
  - Dec. 1872-May 1873, (4 folders) (Box 33)
  - June 1873-Mar. 1874, (4 folders) (Box 34)
  - Apr. 1874-June 1875, (3 folders) (Box 35)
  - July 1875-May 1877, (4 folders) (Box 36)
  - June 1877-1880, (4 folders) (Box 37)
  - 1881-1884, (4 folders) (Box 38)
  - 1885-1893, (4 folders) (Box 39)
  - 1894-1900, (4 folders) (Box 40)
  - 1901-1907, (4 folders) (Box 41)
  - 1908-1919, (4 folders) (Box 42)
  - 1920-1935 and undated, (4 folders) (Box 43)
  - undated, (4 folders) (Box 44)
  - undated, (4 folders) (Box 45)
  - undated, (4 folders) (Box 46)
  - undated, (4 folders) (Box 47)
  - undated, (4 folders) (Box 48)
  - undated, (2 folders) (Box 49)
- Other Materials, (4 boxes; 4 bound volumes)
  - Clippings, (2 folders) (Box 49)
  - Clippings, (3 folders) (Box 50)
  - Genealogy, (2 folders) (Box 51)
  - Miscellaneous; Volumes (Box 52)
  - James A. Nisbet bank book, 1861 (Volume S:2094)
  - James A. Nisbet case book, 1867 (Volume S:2095)
  - James Wingfield Nisbet album, 1869-1930 (Volume M:2096)
  - Junius Wingfield Nisbet notebook, Greek and Latin, 1875 (Volume M:2097)
  - John W. Nisbett diary, 1873-1879 (Volume M:2098)
    Describes social life of Macon University of Georgia, and Nisbett's intellectual interests and family connections.
  - E. A. Nisbet ledger, 1865-1870 (Volume L:3249)